[Applause]
[Alkış]
– Okay, this time on MythBusters
- Evet, bu sefer MythBusters'te
we’re testing like the biggest myth ever!
en büyük mitosu denetleyeceğiz! *
– That cat tastes like chicken?
- Kedinin tavuk gibi tadı olduğunu mu?
– No! Does God exist?!
- Hayır! Tanrı var mı?
– Oh...! So you didn’t want me to put Tittles in the deep fryer?
- Ha...! Yani Tittles'ı fritöze koymamı istemedin mi?
– No...
- Hayır...
– Excuse me.
- Affedersin.
– Now a lot of people may believe that God exists,
- Şimdi çok insan Tanrı'ya inanabilir, ama
but how do we actually prove that God exists?
nasıl gerçekten Tanrı var olduğunu ispatlayabiliriz?
– Well the proof, that most people say, is that
- Şimdi ispat çoğu insana göre bu
they pray to God and he answers their prayer.
Tanrı'ya dua edilir o da duayı kabul eder.
– Right, like when you pray for someone who’s really sick to get better.
- Evet, mesela cidden hasta olana iyileşmesi için dua edersin.
– But that sick person may be getting better due to modern medicine,
- Fakat o hasta birey modern tıp sayesinde iyileşebilir,
the skill of a surgeon or just through the body’s natural healing.
cerrahın hüneri veya vücudun doğal iyileşme sayesinde.
– Exactly! God could be claiming credit for stuff that he has nothing to do with!
- Aynen öyle! Tanrı onunla alakasız şeyler için övgü alabilir!
– So for this experiment to work we need a proper control.
- Bu deneyimin çalışması için bir uygun kontrol lazım.
– And that means kidnapping a terminally ill patient.
- İşte bu ölümcül hasta olan bir kişiyi kaçırmak demek.
– I agree Dr. Adam. – Why, thank you Dr. Jamie.
- Aynı fikirdeyiz Dr. Adem. - Teşekkür ederim Dr. Jamie.
– Let’s go!
- Hadi gidelim!
– Jamie, go! Go, go, go...!
- Hadi Jamie! Hadi, hadi, hadi...!
Don’t make it so loud!
O kadar ses yapma!
– I do the best I can.
Elimden geleni yapıyorum.
– Julie’s body is just, like, riddled with cancer.
- Julie'nin vücudu gerçekten kanser ile dolu.
Until a few hours ago she was receiving all of the
Birkaç saat önce o hastanede batılı
benefits of western medicine in a hospital.
ilaçların bütün faydasını görüyordu.
– Where am I?
- Neredeyim?
– We stole her body,
- Onun bedeni çaldık,
cut off all her treatments
tedavilerine son verdik
and now we’re about to pray to God to cure her.
ve şimdi onu iyileştirmek için Tanrı'ya dua edeceğiz.
– Sshh! You’re part of an experiment.
- Şşş! Sen bir deneyimde parça sın.
– Dear Lord Jesus... I love you a lot...
- Sevgili Tanrı İsa... Seni çok seviyorum...
[Day 3]
Gün 3
– ... my own Mom and Dad...
- ... kendi anam ve babam...
[Day 5] – I just love you God and Lord
Gün 5 - Ben seviyorum seni Tanrı ve Lord
and Jesus and Christmas. Thank you!
ve İsa ve noel. Şükran!
– Well, it’s been 5 days now, and it’s not looking good.
- Evet, 5 gün geçti ve hiç iyi görünmüyor.
– No, it isn’t. I think she’ll be dead within the hour.
- Hayır, iyi değil. Bu saatin içinde ölecek düşünüyorum.
– God! God has really dropped the ball on this one!
- Vay be! Tanrı bunu gerçekten yapayalnız bıraktı.
– He has! In addition to praying for Julie’s recovery
- Evet! Julie'nin iyileşmesine dua etmekle bir de
I’d also prayed to God that Jessica Alba would ask me out on a date.
Tanrı'ya Jessica Alba benimle çıksın diye dua ettim.
So far, she has not called.
Şu ana kadar telefon etmedi.
[Electrical signal for cardiac arrest]
[Kalp durması elektrik sinyalı]
– So, do we call this myth busted?
- Bu mitos yıkılmış sayabilirmiyiz?
– Well, the prayer didn’t work,
- Şey, dua yardım etmedi,
but that could be, because God couldn’t be bothered to save Julie.
ama Tanrı Julie'yi kurtarmaya ilgi duymadı da olabilir.
– Right, because she could, like, go on to be really evil
- Tabii, çünkü o, yani, çok kötü yola gidebilirdi
like Hitler and kill millions of people.
tıpkı Hitler gibi ve milyonlarca insan öldürebilirdi.
– Yet, God allowed Hitler to exist.
- Oysa Hitler'in yaşamasına Tanrı izin verdi.
– So you’re saying that God may exist, but
- Yani sen diyorsun ki Tanrı var olabilir, ama
he just doesn’t give a shit about what happens in the world?
dünyadaki olayları o sikine takmıyor?
– It would explain a lot my friend!
- Bu çok şeyler açıklayabilir dostum!
– Interesting. Either way, I’m calling this myth busted!
- Enteresan. Ama öyle ama böyle, ben bu mitosu yıkılmış sayıyorum!
– Agreed. – Well, that was a real hoot!
- Hemfikirim. - Bu acayıp komik idi!
Next week on the show we’re gonna look at the myth of Allah.
Gelecek şovda biz Allah'ın mitosuna bakacağız.
– Err, no. No, we’re not.
- Ee, hayır. Hayır, bakmıyacağız.
– What? – No, no. Allah is real, totally real!
- Ne? - Hayır, hayır. Allah gerçek, tamamen gerçek!
– Get Adam! He’s the infidel!
- Adem'i ele geçirin! O dur kafir!